William M. Daily collection, 1835-1925 C227
Indiana University Archives
William M. Daily collection
1835-1925
1835-1859
Indiana University Archives
Daily, William M. (William Mitchell), 1812-1877
C227
.6 cubic feet
William Daily was a Methodist minister, and served as president of Indiana University, 1853-1859. The collection includes correspondence, speeches, financial records, administrative records relating to his presidency at Indiana University; most prominent are records relating to charges brought against Daily during his presidency.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Biographical Note
William Mitchell Daily was born in Coshocton, Ohio, in 1812, but was raised in Indiana. He became a Methodist minister at the age of 19 and traveled throughout Indiana preaching. In 1835 he came to Bloomington with his ministry and began studies at Indiana University; he graduated the following year. Daily moved to St. Louis in 1838 and worked as an agent for the Missouri Conference. Shortly after this move he became a professor at St. Charles College. He returned to Indiana in 1840 to recover from a medical condition called hemorrhage of the lungs; upon recovery, he resumed his ministerial career. Daily married Permelia Northcraft in 1843 while he was a minister in Madison, Indiana. Beginning in December 1844 until November 1845 Daily served as Chaplain to the United States House of Representatives. Later he became an agent for Indiana Asbury University (now DePauw) and a member of the Indiana General Conference in 1852.
Upon his return to Bloomington, he became a member of the Board of Trustees at Indiana University on February 10, 1853, and attended his first meeting on July 30, 1853. On August 3, a mere day and a half after the resignation of President Ryors, the Board elected Daily as the third president of the university. Daily's appointment came in the midst of rife sectarianism on campus and in the community. From the beginnings of the university, Presbyterians had constituted most of the school's staff and faculty. This caused the Bloomington community to raise questions about the diversity of the school and about the politics involved. The Indiana Methodist Conference, established in 1832, made it a priority to be represented at the university itself, not just on the board. The sect met with certain opposition. Samuel Bigger, who was elected Indiana governor in 1840, declared that "there was not a Methodist in America with sufficient learning to fill a professor's chair if it were tendered him." (Woodburn p.115) But in 1853 the state had a new governor, Joseph A. Wright, who believed Daily's status as a Methodist and a Democrat could help the institution with its financial troubles. Daily's lack of credentials as an educator, however, caused many members of the IU faculty to feel he was unqualified for such an important position.
Daily's presidency was threatened in July 1858, when Dr. Alexander M. Murphy filed eleven separate charges against him. These charges included incompetence, plagiarism, and incurrence of debt. Other charges concerned incidents of sexual advances towards young women while his wife was away, with these being particularly damning. Murphy maintained that Daily was a "lecher and a lewd man at heart," and that he had used his position to seduce women.
Murphy's statements were compounded by other incidents involving Daily at the end of 1858. Louisa J. Smith, who did not know Daily, stated that on December 29, a strange man had accosted her in the street-the man matched Daily's description. On New Year's Eve, prominent Indianapolis citizens William Wallace and Benjamin Harrison (future President of the United States) testified that they had seen Daily intoxicated in public. These complaints came to the Board with Murphy's charges in January 1859. The body decided that Murphy would need to produce a list of witnesses to sustain the accusations. The next morning, instead of producing this list, Murphy dropped the charges altogether.
Although none of the charges against Daily were substantiated, he resigned his presidency on January 26, 1859, "in order that the unfavorable publicity connected with the trial might not be prejudicial to the University." (Myers p. 328) In a separate farewell address he delivered in February, Daily spoke of the affair as "slimy subterranean damnable conspiracies, brought about by malignant selfish, fiendish, devilish men who are instigated by malice." He also called the members of the faculty "a set of pusillanimous, narrow-minded bigots."
Local Methodists were disappointed by Daily, who was the first major Methodist faculty member at the University. In October 1859, the Indiana Methodist Conference met in Bloomington to decide upon Daily's fate in the association. It was a closed meeting; there were no witnesses presented and no minutes recorded, except for the decision: William Daily was expelled from connection with the conference. Regardless of the university's decision, the Conference felt that Daily should have been free of all suspicion in his position.
During the last years of his life Daily continued his ministry. Anxious to move South, he accepted the appointment of President Lincoln to become hospital chaplain in 1862. He served with the Louisiana Conference beginning in 1869. Daily was in the midst of this new career in the North New Orleans district when he became ill and died a few days later on February 5, 1877. He is buried in Madison, Indiana.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: Correspondence, Financial records, Administrative files, Speeches, and Testimony.
Scope and Content Note
The collection has been organized into five series: Correspondence; Financial records; Speeches; Testimony; and Administrative files. All files are arranged chronologically within their series. Because the Archives holds so little from Daily and his tenure as president of IU, this collection holds both his administrative records and a small amount of personal papers.
The collection begins with a Correspondence series and includes both university and personal correspondence. Prominent are letters written by Daily to his brother, "D.O." in Huntington, Ind., as well as letters written to Theophilus Wylie regarding his appointment at IU.
This is followed by a small series of Financial records, which has two receipts from Samuel Buskirk to the university.
The next series, Speeches, consists of formal addresses from Daily's presidency. Of note is a report on his fiery farewell address in February 1859. This latter item was not written by Daily; it appears to be in T.A. Wylie's hand.
The Testimony series chronicles the charges made against Daily in 1858 and 1859. Included are the initial charges brought by A.M. Murphy in August 1858 and testimony collected by Reverand F.A. Hester on behalf of the Methodist Church on Daily's immorality charges. Witnesses include several prominent Indianpolis citizens, including Benjamin Harrison, then an Indianapolis attorney, who went on to become the 23rd President of the United States. Also found here are responses of the faculty, written by T.A. Wylie.
Within the Administrative files, researchers will find additional records relating to Daily's dismissal, but also a subscription book of donations given to the university after the 1854 destroyed the First College Building, tuition announcements, and a resolution regarding standard text book adoption for the state.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 1135 and 7031
Some materials in this collection were transferred from the University Archives' reference file.
Universities and colleges --Indiana --Bloomington --Administration --History --19th century --Sources.; College presidents --Indiana --Bloomington --Arhives.; College presidents --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Methodist Church --United States --Clergy --Archives.; Methodist Church --United States --Clergy --Correspondence.; Daily, D. O. -- Correspondence; Indiana University -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Daily, William M. (William Mitchell), 1812-1877 -- Archives; Daily, William M. (William Mitchell), 1812-1877 -- Correspondence; Indiana University -- Administration -- History -- 19th century -- Sources; Wylie, Theophilus Adam, 1810-1895 -- Correspondence; Wylie, Theophilus Adam, 1810-1895 -- Correspondence -- Selections; Daily, D. O. -- Correspondence -- Selections
- Correspondence, 1854-1933
  - Buskirk, S. to Unknown, undated (Box 1)
    General
    re: Support of Daily for the Presidency
  - Wylie, T. A. (Box 1)
    - 9 January 1854 (Box 1)
      re: Wylie as potential professor
    - 17 June 1854 (Box 1)
      re: Reverand Elias H. Sabin's honorary degree
  - Lane, Joseph (Box 1)
    Typescripts; origin unknown
    - 20 November 1854 (Box 1)
      re: IU's endowment problems
    - 8 February 1855 (Box 1)
      re: appointment of Loyd Glazebrook
    - 8 February 1855 (Box 1)
      re: criticism of the state legislature
  - to T.A. Wylie (Box 1)
    - 24 March 1855 (Box 1)
      re: Wylie's acceptance of position at IU
    - 7 April 1855 (Box 1)
      re: Unanimous election of Wylie as professor of philosophy and chemistry
  - Woodburn, J. to Whom it May Concern, 8 August 1856 (Box 1)
    re: Sarah McCalla's teaching certification
  - Wylie, T.A., 3 March 1857 (Box 1)
    re: Daily's delay in Indianapolis
  - Rogers, J. to President and Board of Trustees, 3 June 1857 (Box 1)
    re: construction costs
  - Wylie, T.A. (Box 1)
    - 20 July 1858 (Box 1)
      re: Request for Wylie to be present in August
    - 10 January 1859 (Box 1)
      re: Wylie as surrogate president while Daily is out of town
    - 14 January 1859 (Box 1)
      re: Daily's decision to resign
    - 29 January 1859 (Box 1)
      re: Daily's transfer of university register, seal
  - to W.H. English (Box 1)
    Photostats. Originals held by the Indiana Historical Society.
    - 22 November 1859 (Box 1)
      re: supplication for employment
    - 16 December 1859 (Box 1)
      re: English's influence with the administration
  - Cravens, J.A. to W.H. English, 25 November 1860 (Box 1)
    re: thanks for a favor
  - to D.O. Daily (Box 1)
    - 22 November 1864 (Box 1)
      re: William's decision to stay in Indiana
    - 23 July 1865 (Box 1)
      re: William's life in the "Benton Barracks"
    - 2 October 1865 (Box 1)
      re: Lizzie's aborted trip to see D.O. Daily
    - 3 October 1865 (Box 1)
      re: William's commission to Special Agent of the Post Office
    - 10 October 1865 (Box 1)
      re: William's trip to New Orleans
    - 23 March 1866 (Box 1)
      re: William's new life in New Orleans
    - 11 April 1866 (Box 1)
      re: Lizzie's stay with D.O. Daily's family
    - 5 May 1866 (Box 1)
      re: D.O. Daily's possible application as Attorney General
  - Lawton, Lizzie E. (Daily's daughter) to Miss Louise Maxwell (Box 1)
    - 1 February 1898 (Box 1)
      re: memorabilia Lizzie found about her parents
    - 11 July 1898 (Box 1)
      re: contact information for Lizzie and her mother
  - Daily, Thomas to John Cravens, 1 April 1925 (Box 1)
    re: information about burial site of William M. Daily
- Financial records, 1857
  - Receipt for IU signed by Samuel Buskirk (Box 1)
    - 1 January 1857 (Box 1)
    - 8 January 1857 (Box 1)
- Speeches, 1851-1859; undated
  - "Funeral of a Minister, or A Righteous Public Man", 1851 (Box 1)
    Sermon delivered at funeral of first Indiana University President Andrew Wylie
  - Transcript of William Daily's inaugural address, 2 August 1853 (Box 1)
  - "Our Banner." A Baccalaureate to the Graduating Class of the Indiana University, at the Commencement of MDCCCLVI., 3 August 1856 (Box 1)
  - "Dedication of a New House, Indiana University", 30 November 1856 (Box 1)
    Second College Building dedication
  - Baccalaureate to the Law Class of 1857, February 1857 (Box 1)
  - President Daily's Farewell Address, 20 February 1859 (Box 1)
    (This was not written by Daily; looks to have been written by T.A. Wylie)
- Testimony, 1858-1859; undated
  - Testimony (Box 1)
    - in favor of Dr. William Daily, July 1858 (Box 1)
    - "Mrs. Murphy's Testimony reported by T.A. Wylie", 17 August 1858 (Box 1)
  - Rev. F.A. Hester's charge to collect witness testimony for the Daily Trial by S.L. Gillet, 12 January 1859 (Box 1)
  - Statements, 1859 (Box 1)
    - against William Daily by Indianapolis law partners William Wallace and (future U.S. President) Benjamin Harrison, 11 January 1859 (Box 1)
    - of Ellis W. Brown and M.S. Ohn (Box 1)
    - of John Plowman (Box 1)
    - of S.M. Douglas (Box 1)
    - of R.M. Patterson, W.N. Jackson, John Plowman (Box 1)
    - of John F. Wood, James Sulgrane (Box 1)
    - by Louisa J. and Sophia Smith (Box 1)
    - by R. Browning (Box 1)
    - by T.A. Goodwin (Box 1)
  - Faculty response to charges - supportive (Box 1)
  - Faculty response to charges - negative (Box 1)
  - Faculty response to charges against them, 1859 (Box 1)
    Written by T.A. Wylie
  - Faculty response as to why Daily was denied use of College Chapel for his farewell address, 1859 (Box 1)
  - "An Address to the Faculty as is Present Constituted," by James P. Applegate, undated (Box 1)
    Letter to faculty from the sophomore regarding faculty actions against Daily
- Administrative files, 1853-1859; undated
  - Tuition and Boarding fees information, 16 April 1853 (Box 1)
  - Resolution re: uniform text books for state schools, 3 April 1854 (Box 1)
  - Seminary Square - subscription/donors for rebuilding after the 1854 fire (Box 1)
  - Letters written to parents of students requesting dismissal after resignation of Pres. Daily, February 1859 (Box 1)
  - Report on activities surrounding Daily's departure to the Board of Trustees, undated (Box 1)